A Finding Aid to the Isabella Howland papers, 1899-1979, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Isabella Howland papers
1899-1979
Archives of American Art
Howland, Isabella, 1895-1974
AAA.howlisab
Archival Resource Key
1.2 Linear feet
The papers of artist Isabella Howland measure 1.2 linear feet and date from 1899-1979. The collection documents her career through biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, writings, printed material, artwork, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter, sculptor, caricaturist, and portraitist Isabella Howland measure 1.2 linear feet and date from 1899-1979. Correspondence makes up about a third of the collection, with the remainder comprised of biographical material, writings, printed material, photographs, and artworks.
Correspondence is found between Isabella Howland and other artists or dealers. Among these are Eugenie Gershoy, Henry Strater, Edith Halpert, Peggy Bacon, Forbes Watson, Jerry Bywaters, Adolph Dehn and Dorothea Greenbaum. Letters from Juliana Force, the first director of the Whitney Museum of American Art, are present. Many invitations to exhibit are included. The collection includes a small number of letters with Howland's family. She maintained written communication with several individuals over decades.
The biographical material contains Isabella Howland's handwritten notes and typed documents about her life. Some legal documents and financial records are present. The writing series includes her story 'Willy Nilly' with accompanying illustrations of animals, in addition to some other writings. The artwork series includes sketches and sketchbooks from childhood into adulthood. Photographs include images of Howland as well as her paintings and portraits.
Biographical / Historical
Isabella Howland (1895-1974) lived and worked in New York City. She drew portraits, painted on canvas, sketched on paper, and sculpted caricature busts of people in the art world. She wrote that she could do anything with her hands.
Howland was born in Brookline, Massachusetts. From her youth she knew she wanted to be an artist. She had her earliest artistic training at age 16. Her art education included time at the Boston Museum School and the Art Students League in New York City. She completed her secondary education in France and Germany, moved back to the United States afterwards, and in 1920 travelled again to Europe. In 1922 she settled in Greenwich Village and spent summers in Woodstock to paint landscapes and still-lifes. She actively painted in the 1920s, and had three shows in 1927, 1929, and 1931. During the Depression she worked for the Public Works of Art Project and the Works Progress Administration. In 1934 she married Armando Zegri, and they divorced in 1937. While they were married they owned a club in the West Village named The Café Latino. She began teaching at a private school in the early 1940s while dealing with some personal difficulties. She found religion which comforted her as she dealt with her mother's declining health and her sister's waning mental state.
Howland had many friends in the art world and regularly received requests to exhibit at museums. She became known as an accomplished portrait artist, and she was commissioned many times to execute drawings or sculptures. She dabbled in writing and illustrating stories, and produced a set of 33 Christmas cards featuring two monks.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated between 1975-1976 by Mrs. Martha Craig and Barbara Summer. Three photographs of works of art were donated by Eugenie Gershoy in 1979.
Arrangement
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1901-1972 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1917-1973 (22 folders; Box 1)
Series 3, Writings, 1935-1964 (8 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1928-1976 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1900-1979 (4 folders; Box 1, OV 2)
Series 6: Artwork, 1899-circa 1940s (8 folders; Box 1, OV 2)
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Portrait painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Caricaturists -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Women painters; Women sculptors; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Photographs; Bacon, Peggy, 1895-1987; Strater, Henry, 1896-; Watson, Forbes, 1880-1960; Greenbaum, Dorothea S.; Halpert, Edith Gregor, 1900-1970; Gershoy, Eugenie, 1901?-1983 or 6; Force, Juliana, 1876-1948; Bywaters, Jerry; Dehn, Adolf, 1895-1968
- Biographical Material, 1901-1972; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes childhood memorabilia and financial records. Legal documents include dissolving of a partnership between Howland and her then-husband (Armando Zegri) from their partner for the business Café Latino. Another letter from an attorney discusses Howland's divorce from Zegri. One address book is present.
  - Address Book, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Childhood Memorabilia, 1901-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial Records, 1938-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Legal Documents, 1935-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1917-1973; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 22 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence makes up about one third of the collection. Howland corresponded with friends and colleagues over many decades. There are letters or postcards from various people, including Eugenie Gershoy, Henry Strater, Edith Halpert, Peggy Bacon, Forbes Watson, Jerry Bywaters, Adolph Dehn, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, and Dorothea Greenbaum. Also present are a few letters regarding her work in the Treasury Department's Public Works of Art Project and the Works Progress Administration. Many letters are from museums, galleries, or organizations inviting her to participate in exhibits or thanking her for taking part. Other letters document sales of artworks.
  - A, miscellaneous, 1917-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B, miscellaneous, 1930-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bacon, Peggy, 1918-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - C, miscellaneous, 1933-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - D, miscellaneous, 1933-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - F, miscellaneous, 1954-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Father of Isabella Howland, 1911-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - G, miscellaneous, 1932-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Halpert, Edith, 1933-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - H, miscellaneous, 1911-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - J, miscellaneous, 1938-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - K, miscellaneous, 1933-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - M, miscellaneous, 1917-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mc, miscellaneous, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - P, miscellaneous, circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - R, miscellaneous, 1936-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Strater, Henry, 1953-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - S, miscellaneous, 1930-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Unknown or First Name Only, 1932-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Watson, Forbes, 1947-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1932-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - W, miscellaneous, 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Writings, 1935-1964; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 8 Folders Box 1
  Writings include handwritten and typed autobiographical materials. There are some notes related to her art career. Howland wrote a story called 'Willy Nilly,' and the records contain handwritten and typed copies as well as illustrations. Also included are some poems and one translation by the artist from the Book of Proverbs. A photocopy of a guestbook from Café Latino and some unidentified writings complete the series.
  - Autobiographical, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Notes re Art Career, 1940-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Poetry and Translations, circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Willy Nilly", 1959-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30-32)
  - Cafe Latino Guestbook (photocopy), 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Unidentified Writings, 1935-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Printed Material, 1928-1976; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Box 1
  Printed material includes a set of 33 Christmas cards Howland designed. Exhibition pamphlets involve Howland and other artists. Many clippings from newspapers including photos of artists, politicians, and Howland sculptures.
  - Christmas Cards Designed by Isabella Howland, circa 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
  - Exhibition Materials, 1928-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1924-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1938-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Photographs, circa 1900-1979; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1, OV 2
  Photographs depict Howland and her works. Also included are photos by Eugenie Gershoy of works by Howland. Portraits of the artist and member of the Lost Generation Henry Strater are present.
  - Howland, Isabella, circa 1900-circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Howland Artwork, circa 1920s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Photos by Eugenie Gershoy of Works by Isabella Howland, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Portraits of Henry Strater, circa 1900-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Oversized material housed in OV 2.
  - Oversize Portrait of Henry Strater from Box 1, Folder 43, circa 1900-1979; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)
- Artwork, 1899-circa 1940s; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 8 Folders Box 1, OV 2
  Artwork makes up a significant portion of the collection. Many sketchbooks from Howland's childhood, sketches from a trip to Jamaica (probably), and other loose sketches. Also found are figure studies, ink drawings, landscapes, two watercolors with tropical iconography (probably Jamaica), and two sketches from 1914 with war theme.
  - Early Childhood Drawings, 1899-1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Early Childhood Drawings, 1903-1909; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1910s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1910s-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Sketches, circa 1930s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Sketches, 1899-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
  - Oversize Figure and landscape sketches, 1899-circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)
  - Oversize Sketches about War, 1914; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)